India showed restraint after the
parliament attacks, right?
>> Greatly. Greatly
>> showed restraint after the Mumbai
attacks of 2008.
>> Yes indeed.
>> But they didn't show any restraint this
time around when operation Synindhur
happened in Pelgam where it was a 4-day
high intensity sort of war that
happened. What what do you think changed
over in the course of these two decades
>> at the CIA? We called the Indian policy
um strategic patience.
The the Indian government would have
been perfectly within its rights to
respond respond by striking Pakistan and
they didn't.
And I remember at the White House people
were saying, "Wow, the Indians are
really exhibiting a very mature foreign
policy here." We expected the Indians to
to strike back and they didn't.
And that kept the the world from what
might have been a nuclear exchange,
>> right?
>> But India's gotten to the point where
they can't risk strategic patience being
misunderstood as weakness.
And so they had to respond
>> right
>> now. The question the question now that
CIA analysts are likely asking
themselves are did the Pakistanis learn
their lesson not to keep poking the
hornets's nest and expecting to not be
stung. Just a couple of months later in
March of 2002 we raided a Lashkar Itaya
safe house in Lahore.
>> Okay. And and in that house we captured
three Lashkarayaba fighters who had with
them a copy of the al-Qaeda training
manual.
And it was the first time
analytically that we were able to
connect Lashkaraya with al-Qaeda. The
very first time. I remember receiving a
cable from the from the deputy director
of the CIA for intelligence
congratulating us on finding this
training manual saying it was the very
first time that we could attach the
Pakistani government
to al-Qaeda.
>> What stopped you from going after
Pakistan? Then you you have the first
smoking gun of a inextricably linked ISI
because the le or the JM jud the various
names that they come up with essentially
ISI proxies propped up by the Pakistani
government and now they have a direct
correct
>> yes
>> why why didn't you ever bring this up
>> that was a decision that was made at the
white house
>> and the decision was that that the
relationship is bigger than India
Pakistan
at least temporarily the relationship
we needed the Pakistanis actually more
than they needed us at that point we
were happy to throw money at them that's
what they responded to
>> but we really needed them to let us base
our drones in Baluchistan for example um
have what's called a picket line CIA
officers all the way up and down the
border with uh with Afghanistan.
>> So So from Wazinistan all the way down
to Baluchistan
>> to
>> Baluchistan.
>> We we needed a presence in Pashaw. We
needed a presence in Queda. We needed a
presence in Karachi and Lahore. And we
needed for them to say yes to everything
that we wanted to do. And so a decision
was made at the White House that if we
strategically ignore
this terrorism problem visa v India
the relationship would be much easier to
negotiate and and so that's what we did.
I'll tell you one other thing years
later in 2008
>> um I had I had left the CIA. I had blown
the whistle already and I was working as
a as a uh counterterrorism advisor to
ABC News, one of the big news networks
here in the United States.
>> And um
and uh I got a call saying, "Are you
watching the news?" I said, "No, it was
the night before Thanksgiving, so it's a
major American holiday. Major holiday."
I said, "No, I I'm I'm not watching the
news. Uh there's been a an enormous
terrorist attack in Mumbai. They're
attacking hotels. They're attacking
Jewish centers. They're attacking this
and attacking that." I said, "Oh my
god." They said, "Um,
can you come into the studio and talk
about this?" I said, "Of course."
Everybody else was on vacation because
it's the eve of a major holiday.
>> Yes. So, I jump in the shower, I shave,
and as I'm getting dressed, my wife, who
was still in the CIA at the time, she
said, "You should watch, while you're
getting dressed, you should watch what
the other networks are saying about
this." So, I I go to CNN, they said,
"Alqaeda." I go to Fox, al-Qaeda, MSNBC,
it's al-Qaeda. And these are all friends
of mine who were saying it. And I said
to my wife, I don't think this is
al-Qaeda.
She said,
"Wow, you better really be sure of
yourself if you're going to put your
reputation on the line and tell the
entire country that this is not
al-Qaeda." So, I I drove down to ABC
News to the studio.
>> Mhm.
>> And they wired me up and I was talking
to the reporter in New York and I said,
"Listen, I don't think this is al-Qaeda.
I think this is this is the Pakistani
uh supported Kashmir groups." I said,
'Ala doesn't care about India. They
don't have any problem with the Indians.
Their fight is with us.
>> Yes.
>> And he said, "Oh my god." He said, "You
should You're going to need to be 100%
sure because everybody is saying it's
al-Qaeda." And I said, "I I was in the
CIA long enough that I can say that I
feel strongly this is not al-Qaeda." And
so I went on the air and I was the only
person that said I believe that these
are Pakistani Kashmir separatist groups
supported by the Pakistani ISI.
>> Right?
>> And that turned out to be exactly the
case
>> to the point where ABC News made
television commercials saying ABC News
the Mumbai attacks we were the only ones
that got it right.
>> Right. But there was a bigger issue
here, bigger story here and the story
was that Pakistan was committing
terrorism in India
>> and nobody did anything about it.
>> During your time in Pakistan 2002 3,
four around that time
>> another very dangerous threat to
humanity was uh Dr. AQ Khan's
>> Oh yes,
>> right.
>> Yes. Yes. So we we got to know that
nuclear material was being smuggled out
to the North Koreans.
>> Yes.
>> There was there was proliferation going
on with Libyan nuclear material as well
going into Pakistan. All of that started
coming out
>> when you were there in Pakistan. Yes.
When you got this on your desk, what was
the first thing you thought? You guys
are going after terrorists. Here's
Pakistan assembling nuclear bombs and
selling it in the gray market or black
market. That's an outstanding question
and a very important one. It it never
crossed my desk. I was specifically
counterterrorism,
but a colleague of mine,
this was his entire life was dealing
with AQ Khan.
Well,
if we had taken, you know, the Israeli
approach, we would have just killed him.
He was easy enough to find. We knew
where he lived. We knew how he spent his
day.
But he also had the support of the Saudi
government. And the Saudis came to us
and said, "Please leave him alone.
Please,
we like Aukan. We're working with Aukan.
We're close to the Pakistanis." They
even named Fiselabad after King Fisil.
Just leave him alone.
Um, this was a mistake that the US
government made not confronting AQN
headon. And and I'll add too, later on
when I went to the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee staff as the chief
investigator,
I worked for a man
who was a journalist before going to the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee
Staff. And he and his wife wrote a book
that was first titled The Man from
Pakistan. And they the title was changed
in the paperback version to the nuclear
jihadist. It was the most detailed book
ever written about AQ Khan. And they
asked more than two dozen
CIA officers and United Nations IAEA
officials
exactly the same question that you just
asked me. Hm.
>> I was surprised that they got so many
people to speak with them freely and
openly, but they all told the same
thing.
They said that
there were instructions from the White
House
not to attack Aukan
and it had to be because the Saudis were
demanding it, insisting on it. We often
wondered, and I have no proof,
this is just my own speculation. We
often wondered if it was because the
Saudis were also building a nuclear
capability.
>> Yeah, I think that's something we should
probably be thinking about.
>> Well, when you put this into context and
you talk about the Saudi Pakistan Mutual
Defense Pact that was just signed a few
months ago.
>> Yes.
>> Is Saudi Arabia basically calling in its
investment? I think yes. But you know, I
have to laugh about this mutual defense
pact.
>> I don't know if you've ever spent any
time in Saudi Arabia,
>> but almost the entire Saudi military is
Pakistanis.
No Saudis going to join the military
unless they're going to make him a
general. You know, there are a lot of
bedawins in the Saudi military, but you
go straight in as an officer. If you're
a Saudi citizen, you're going to start
as an officer. There are no there are no
privates or corporals who are Saudi.
They're all Pakistani. All of them.
>> It's the Pakistanis that protect Saudi
Arabia.
>> But how realistic is on the ground?
>> But how realistic is a nuclear umbrella
though? That's what is I mean that at
least some of the doomsayers in India
think of it like that.
>> Yeah. I don't think it is realistic.
Yeah.
>> No, I don't think it's realistic.
>> When this AQ Khan uh thing happened and
it was brought up, what was this Saudi
Arabia hold on America? Now you have
Saudi terrorists taking out the 9/11
towers.
>> That's right.
>> Saudi Arabia actively lobbying to
protect one of the most dangerous men at
least in the last quarter century at
least in this region. and then
eventually perve Musharov also pardoning
AQ Khan therefore ending all
investigations. What is this compulsion
that America has with dictators and this
love story?
>> That is that is one of the most
difficult questions that you could ask.
You know we we like to we like to try to
convince the world that we are a shining
beacon of hope for democracy and human
rights and equality and it's just simply
not true.
Um our our foreign relations
um
our foreign relations are based on
on our national needs at any given
moment. We don't do things because
they're the right thing to do.
>> We do them because they happen to be
good for us that day.
Which is why we get into bed with so
many dictators around the world. which
is why we get into bed with with so many
politicians who are so extreme in their
personal politics that it makes no sense
to the American people. Why are we in
bed with Benjamin Netanyahu right now
when we've known Netanyahu since the
1980s as an extremist?
>> Yes,
>> because it's uh it's it's the easy thing
to do and it serves our purposes, you
know, today. That may change tomorrow,
but but today it's okay. You know, I I
worked for an ambassador in Bahrain who
was an absolutely lovely man.
And he he said one day, I still remember
this. I was young and impressionable.
And he said, you know, our foreign
policy in in Saudi Arabia
really is as simple as
we buy their oil and they buy our
weapons.
>> That's it.
>> That's it. That's it. That's the basis.
He said, "You spend your career in the
Middle East. I've spent my entire adult
life in the Middle East." He said, "I
don't like the Saudis. They don't like
us.
But we pretend to have this special
relationship."
Right? Even in the American embassy, I
my first overseas tour was in Saudi
Arabia and I remember an enormous
photograph. It had to be 2 meters across
and it was President Franklin Roosevelt
and King uh Abdul Aziz Iben Sud, the
founder of Saudi Arabia in the back of a
car together.
>> And this was supposed to be emblematic
of our special relationship with the
Saudis.
But
when I first arrived in Saudi Arabia,
um I was placed in um embassy housing.
So I was living in in an apartment in
the diplomatic quarter and I would walk
a block or two to the to the embassy and
go in the back entrance of the embassy
and every day my first 3 days I would
say to this Saudi guard national saying
Saudi Arabia National Guard uh officer
standing there salamukum.
The response of course is walaykumalam.
>> Yes.
>> He would he would ignore me. So the next
day I went in and I saidamulaykum
>> and he ignored me. The third day I went
in and I saidalamu
alaykum good morning and peace be upon
you.
>> He ignored me and I stopped and I said
to him what's your problem?
And he said to me in English he said
you are hired help.
we paid for you to come here and defend
us. We are not friends.
>> And I said, you know what? You're right.
We aren't friends. I don't like you and
I don't like any of your compatriots.
None of them.
>> Right.
>> And then I never spoke to him again. But
that was the US Saudi relationship in a
nutshell.
>> Do you think Saudi Arabia knows this
now? cuz uh with this mutual defense
pact again I bring I keep coming back to
the nuclear thing and them sort of you
know basically seeking nuclear
deterrence with the help of Pakistan
then it it appears with the new with the
with this Trump regime that a certain
amount of American retrenchment has
happened in the region where it's almost
like a hemispheric defense now that
America is focusing on
>> so Saudi Arabia always had the US for
its back now that US is not at least it
appears that it's not highly dependent
on uh Saudi oil, Saudi energy. Do you
think Saudi Arabia is doing this as an
insurance pack?
>> Absolutely. Yes. And it's not just Saudi
Arabia, it's Kuwait as well. Kuwait last
year made a purchase of uh not made a
purchase made a sale of oil to China and
for the very first time ever took
payment in yuan.
>> Yeah. First time ever that payment was
not in dollars. So, I think everybody is
coming around to the notion that here in
the United States, we're sitting on an
ocean of oil. Okay? We have shale oil
enough to last us 500 years. We don't
need Middle Eastern oil. We buy it
because it's good for relations.
>> Yes.
>> Because we we buy it and then they buy
our weapon systems,
>> right?
>> So, we continue to do that. But but when
it when push comes to shove, we don't
need the Saudis anymore.
>> We don't Mhm. And so they're hedging
their bets. They're they're improving
their relations with China. They're
improving their relations with India,
which is a huge market and in need of
oil.
>> Yes.
>> And and you know, if the if the Indians
are going to have problems, especially
from the United States, buying Russian
oil or Russian natural gas, they should
just buy it from Saudi Arabia. Makes it
even easier,
>> right? Yeah. Absolutely. So I think
we're we're seeing a a transformation
here
>> in in the the way the world operates.
>> Very dynamic geopolitical shift is being
viewed here. That's why conversation
with you uh someone in the field and who
has historical context. I mean it's it's
fantastic.